A Guide to the Secretary of Public Safety and Homeland Security records, 2006-2013 (bulk 2010-2013)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Secretary of Public Safety and Homeland Security records, 2006-2013 (bulk 2010-2013)
The Library of Virginia
51122
7 cu. ft. (7 boxes)
Secretary of Public Safety and Homeland Security
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected and confidential information is restricted from public access for 75 years per code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Restricted records in this collection have been sealed but not removed from the collection. Types of sealed information may include, but are not limited to: social security numbers, Department of Corrections inmate material, mediation and settlement discussions, and attorney-client privileged material.
Acquisition Information
This series was transferred by the office of the Secretary of Public Safety and Homeland Security in January 2014.
Biographical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governor's top management team.
The office of the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was created on April 8, 1972. Originally, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety oversaw the State Highway Commission, Division of Motor Vehicles, Department of State Police, Highway Safety Division, Office of Emergency Services, Department of Military Affairs, Virginia State Crime Commission, and the Law Enforcement Officers Training Standards Commission. Since that time, the Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature established separate secretariats for transportation and public safety, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were again combined. Finally, the two became separate offices on February 22, 1990, and have remained separate in the years since.
The Secretary of Public Safety is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, is appointed by the governor, and is subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. Throughout Governor Robert F. McDonnell's next term (2010-2014), the Secretary of Public Safety was responsible for the direction of, or had jurisdiction over 11 state agencies and boards. The agencies and boards under the heading of the Secretary of Public Safety during the previous McDonnell administration were: Alcoholic Beverage Control Authority, Commonwealth's Attorney's Services Council, Department of Corrections, Department of Criminal Justice Services, Department of Emergency Management, Department of Fire Programs, Department of Forensic Sciences, Department of Juvenile Justice, Department of Military Affairs, the Virginia State Police, and the Department of Veterans Services. Legislation in 2010 by Governor previous McDonnell moved the Department of Veterans Services (DVS) from the Office of Public Safety to the Office of Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security along with the Virginia War Memorial.
On December 3, 2009, Governor-elect Robert F. McDonnell appointed Marla Graff Decker as his Secretary of Public Safety. Prior to taking this position, Decker had served as the Deputy Attorney General of Public Safety and Enforcement Division in the Office of the Attorney General of Virginia. There she supervised drafting of criminal legislation, staffing of crime prevention initiatives and the initiation of criminal prosecutions. On October 1, 2013, Governor McDonnell appointed Decker to the Court of Appeals of Virginia to fill Judge Larry Elder's seat vacancy (September 4, 2013). Thus, on November 1, 2013 Bryan Michael Rhode was appointed as Secretary of Public Safety. Rhode previously served as the Commissioner of the Department of Alcoholic Beverage Control and Deputy Secretary of Public Safety.
Some of the key initiatives, advisory boards, and task forces during Decker and Rhode's tenure concerned prisoner reentry programs, substance abuse prevention, domestic violence prevention and response, statewide gang prevention and alternatives of non-violent offenders.
Scope and Content
The Secretary of Public Safety records consists of 7 archival boxes and are divided into 3 series. This collection documents the activities of the Office of the Secretary of Public Safety, as well as the agencies and boards that fell under its purview during the McDonnell administration. These records consists of correspondence, agendas, legislative files, memoranda, reports, council and board briefs, and other working papers.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Weekly Reports
II. Correspondence
III. Administrative Records
IV. Subject Files
Contents List
- Weekly Reports, 2010 Jan-Oct., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 1-2)
  Reports for the Governor's office that document each agency's activities for that week including legislation, special projects, events, agency matters, social media metrics, media requests, and news articles.
  Chronologically
  - 2010 Jan 28. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 2010 Feb 04. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 2010 Feb 11. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 2010 Feb 25. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 2010 Mar 04. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 2010 Mar 11. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 2010 Mar 11. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 2010 Mar 18. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 2010 Mar 25. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 2010 Apr 01. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 2010 Apr 08. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 2010 Apr 15. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 2010 Apr 22. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 2010 Apr 29. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 2010 May 06. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 2010 May 13. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 2010 May 20. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 2010 May 27. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 2010 May 31. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 2010 June 01. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 2010 June 08. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 2010 June 10. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 2010 June 17. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 2010 June 24. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 2010 July 1. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 2010 July 8. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 2010 July 15. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 2010 July 22. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 2010 July 29. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 2010 Aug 5. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 2010 Aug 12. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 2010 Aug 19. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 2010 Aug 26. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 2010 Sept 2. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 2010 Sept 9. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 2010 Sept 16. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 2010 Sept 23. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 2010 Sept 30. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 2010 Oct 7. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 2010 Oct 14. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 2010 Oct 21. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 2010 Oct 28. (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 2010-2012., Extent: 1 box. (Box 3)
  Correspondence to and from the Secretary of Public Safety from other government officials, agencies, and the public. Letters are about a variety of topics including agency activities and topics that fall under the purview of Public Safety such as the drinking age, traffic tickets, parole, veteran benefits, and other issues.
  Alphabetically by last name
  - A. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - B. (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - C. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - D. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - E. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - F. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - G. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - H. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - J. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - K. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - L. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - M. (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
  - N. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - O. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - P. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - R. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - S. (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - T. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - V. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - W. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Y. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Z. (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Administrative Records, 2006-2013., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 4-5)
  Records documenting the activities of the Secretary of Public Safety and the agencies that fall under its scope including invitations, programs, agency activities and initiatives, and other events.
  - Badges for Baseball, 2006-2010. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Thank You's and Congratulations, 2009-2010. (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - 2010 Forecast, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Appointment Requests, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - Audits, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Boards and Commissions, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 7b)
  - Decision Sheets. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - VA Alcoholic Beverage Control. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Dept. of Corrections, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Dept. of Corrections Education Audit, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Dept. of Criminal Justice Services, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Dept. of Emergency Management, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Dept. of Fire Programs, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Dept. of Juvenile Justice, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Dept. of Military Affairs, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Dept. of Virginia State Police, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Dept. of Veteran's Affairs, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Governor's Cabinet Exercise (Hurricane Preparedness), 2010. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Invitations - Declined, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Jens Soering, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Jung Kwang Kim, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Nonviolent Task force, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Prisoner Re-Entry, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Re-Entry Council Meetings, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 25-26)
  - Regional Gangs Meeting, 2010. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Reports to the General Assembly, 2010-2011. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Simple Pardon Summary, 2010. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Strategic Plan, 2010. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Temporary Assignment Reports, 2010. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Agency Overviews, 2011. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Asset Forfeiture, 2010. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Decision Tracking, 2011 Jan-July. (Box 5, Folder 8-10)
  - Familial DNA Searches, 2011. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Invitations - Accepted, 2011. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Invitations - Declined, 2011. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Line of Duty Deaths - Buchanan County, 2011. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Public Safety Conference, 2011. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Public Safety Stake holders Executive Advisory Board, 2011. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Agency Preparedness Assessments, 2012. (Box 5, Folder 17-18)
  - Briefing Book - Sussex I and II, 2013. (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Subject Files, 2010-2013., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 6-7)
  These files document specific activities or events involving the Secretary of Public Safety and the agencies the Secretary oversees.
  Alphabetically
  - Adult Alternative Program. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Agency Accomplishments. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Agency Consolidation. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Agency Head Retreat. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Alternatives for Non-Violent Offenders Task force, 2011 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Analysis of Emergency Plans. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Annual Report, 2010. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Annual Report, 2011. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Arizona Immigration Legislation, 2010 June 24. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Commission on Military Installations. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Criminal Justice Conference. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Drive to Work, 2013. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - E. Daly Arrest, 2013. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Experience and Education in Primary and Secondary Education. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - General Assembly Session Public Safety Bills, 2012. (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - General Assembly Session Public Safety Bills, 2013. (Box 6, Folder 16-19)
  - Governor's Legislative Agenda, 2012. (Box 6, Folder 20-22)
  - Hanover and River North, 2012. (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Hurricane Irene, 2011. (Box 6, Folder 24-25)
  - Hurricane Sandy, 2012. (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - JROTC Cadet Corps, 2011. (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Judicial Nominees, 2013. (Box 6, Folder 28-29)
  - Juvenile Justice. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Legislative Package for Transportation Funding and Reform, 2011. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Line of Duty Act, 2010 Jan 7. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Mecklenburg Visit, 2011. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - National Boy scout Jamboree, 2010. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Non-Violent Offenders Task force. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Presidential Inauguration, 2013. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Press Conference, 2010 Dec 16. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Prisoner Re-Entry. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Re-Entry Initiative. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Rebuilding Bridges. 2013 (Box 7, Folder 11-12)
  - Recidivism. (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Report of the Policy Transition Committee on Public Safety, 2009-2010. (Box 7, Folder 14-17)
  - Review of State Spending, 2011. (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - School and Campus Safety Task force, 2013. (Box 7, Folder 19-25)
  - Sequestration Impacts on Public Safety Agencies. (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Virginia Alcohol and Beverage Control License Enforcement. (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Virginia Alcohol and Beverage Control Privatization Briefing. (Box 7, Folder 28)